Guide to the William A. Speck Collection of Goetheana: General Ephemera
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
William A. Speck collection of Goetheana: general ephemera
1766-1999
YCGL MSS 27
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
3.13
(14 boxes) + 21 broadside folders
The William A. Speck Collection of Goetheana: General Ephemera is an artificial collection of miscellaneous, non-book materials long associated with the Speck Collection but previously uncataloged. The collection demonstrates how Goethe and his works entered into the popular culture in the late nineteenth century and early decades of the twentieth. The collection includes a few items relating directly to Goethe, such as pens that he used and his grandfather Textor's seal, as well as items intended for the tourist market, probably purchased in the streets of Weimar around the turn of the twentieth century. Printed ephemera in the collection includes inflation money from the 1920s, or "Notgeld," printed with quotations from Goethe and illustrations from his works; advertising trade cards and other advertising materials; posters; cigar boxes; matchbooks; stationery; postcards; photographs of actors in Goethe-related roles; and wall hangings. Three-dimensional items include figurines of characters from Faust, plaques featuring Goethe's image, a fragment of his house, pressed flowers from his garden, and a lock of Schiller's hair.
Speck, William A. (William Alfred), 1864-1928
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Acquired at various times and from various sources.
Custodial History
The Speck Collection of Goetheana: General Ephemera consists chiefly of material that has long been associated with the William A. Speck Collection of Goetheana but has never before been cataloged. A significant portion of the material came to the library as part of the Faust collection assembled by George Wilhelm Heinrich Ehrhardt and acquired by William A. Speck in 1923. While much of that collection was cataloged, some remained in various "miscellaneous" files or "object" boxes. (Ehrhardt items usually bear tiny stickers with a number in ink in a German hand.) Other items seem to have been saved by Speck or sent to him and his successors because people knew of their obsessive interest in Goethe—postage stamps, advertising trade cards, clippings, post cards. The provenance of particular items, when known, has been recorded in the list of collection contents.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
Associated Materials: William A. Speck Collection of Goetheana: Manuscripts (YCGL MSS 6), William A. Speck Collection of Goetheana: Music (YCGL MSS 9), William A. Speck Collection of Prints (YCGL MSS 11), William A. Speck collection of Goetheana: Theater Ephemera (YCGL MSS 24), and William A. Speck Collection of Goetheana: Original Artwork (YCGL MSS 26), Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library.
William A. Speck (1864-1928)
William A. Speck, the son of German immigrants, was born in New York City in 1864. A pharmacist by profession, he amassed the largest Goethe collection outside of Germany. In 1913, he and his collection came from Haverstraw, New York to Yale, where he served as curator of the Speck Collection until his death in 1928. For further biographical information on William A. Speck and a general history and description of the Speck Collection, see the finding aid for the William A. Speck Collection of Goetheana: Manuscripts (YCGL MSS 6).
Scope and Contents
The William A. Speck Collection of Goetheana: General Ephemera is an artificial collection of miscellaneous, non-book materials long associated with the Speck Collection but previously uncataloged. These are artifacts that were not considered important enough to catalog separately or to include in the William A. Speck Collection of Goetheana: Original Artwork. The quality and interest of the material vary widely. There are historical souvenirs of some significance, such as pens used by Goethe or his grandfather Textor's seal, as well as cheap tourist items, probably purchased in the streets of Weimar around the turn of the twentieth century. The inflation money printed the 1920s is oddly moving: in the throes of an economic crisis that wiped out fortunes large and small, German cities and towns adorned their "Notgeld" with quotations from Goethe and illustrations from his works. Some of the items in the collection could be loved only by the dedicated Goethe afficionado—the illustration of his coach, for instance, or the pressed flowers from his garden, gathered decades after his death.
If the collection has significance, it is to demonstrate how Goethe and his works entered into the popular culture in the late nineteenth century and early decades of the twentieth. From costume jewelry to lithopanes to cigar boxes and candy wrappers, Goethe must have been present to the popular imagination, as reflected in the products and advertising of the period. Certain themes predominate in the collection: Faust in his study, Gretchen at her spinning wheel, Faust and Mephisto in conversation, Faust and Gretchen walking in the garden, Goethe and Schiller together—these iconic motifs recur again and again, on matchboxes, in wall hangings, on postcards, in jokes.
Arrangement
Organized into five series: I. Flat Objects, Paintings, Photographs and Illustrations, 1766-1999. II. Goethe in Adverstising, 1897-1949. III. Postcards and Commercial Photographs, 1897-1956. IV. Objects, 1897-1989. V. Posters and Broadsheets, 1897-1932.
Authors, German; German literature -- 18th century; German literature -- 19th century; Weimar (Germany) -- Intellectual life; Figurines; Notgelden; Postcards; Plaques (flat objects); Printed ephemera; Photographs; Posters; Quill pens; Seals (artifacts); Souvenirs; Trade cards (advertising); Goethe, Johann Wolfgang von, 1749-1832; Goethe, Johann Wolfgang von, 1749-1832 ( Characters); Goethe, Johann Wolfgang von, 1749-1832 ( Faust, Illustrations); Schiller, Friedrich, 1759-1805; Speck, William A. (William Alfred), 1864-1928; Textor, Johann Jost, 1739-1792; Goethe-Haus (Frankfurt am Main, Germany)
- Flat Objects, Paintings, Photographs and Illustrations, 1766-1999; Series I; (3 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I. consists of two-dimensional printed ephemera, photographs and paintings relating to Goethe and Schiller, as well as flat wall hangings and plaques, leaves from Goethe and Schiller's coffins, a swatch of Schiller's waistcoat, pens used by Goethe, and an ivory carving of Schiller.
  - German inflation money ("Notgeld"), 1918-1923; Circa 170 items, including duplicates (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
    Currency printed by German cities during the inflation, all with quotations from Goethe or images relating to Goethe or his works Arranged partly by place of origin, partly by theme.
  - Writing paper with Goethe motifs, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    One set, commemorating the centenary of Goethe's death in 1932, features photographs of Goethe sites and artifacts as well as a few contemporary photographs of members of Die Gesellschaft der Freunde Weimars, including one showing Elisabeth Förster-Nietzsche.
  - Paper seals ("Siegelmarken"), 1905-1949; 10 items (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Seals intended to be affixed to letter envelopes, with themes relating to Goethe and Schiller.
  - Postage stamps, postage cancellations, circa 1905-1999; Circa 25 items (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Assorted single stamps, sheets, and stamped envelopes with Goethe and Schiller themes.
  - Coffin leaves, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Immediate Source of Acquisition
    Provenance: Accompanied by a note in William A. Speck's hand, "These leaves Frank Claudy, translator of 'Faust,' brought from Weimar. They were sent to me by his son." (Frank Claudy, 1844-1919).
    Ivy leaf from Schiller's coffin, 2 bay leaves from Goethe's coffin, and an unidentified pressed flower
  - Bookplates, 1932-1958; 15 items (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Bookplates with Goethe images or content, including a clipped facsimile of Goethe's book label and a commemorative set of bookplates from the Goethe year 1932.
  - Goethe grapes, undated; 30 x 22 cm. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Colored print depicting the grape variety named for Goethe, one of several varieties created by E. S. Rogers in the mid nineteenth century, known as Rogers' Hybrids.
  - Paper towels, 1998; 3 sheets (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Provenance: Because the towels were apparently not distributed locally in Connecticut, the curator wrote to Georgia Pacific and asked for a roll of them, which was kindly sent by the manufacturer.
    Paper towels distributed under the Sparkle label by Georgia Pacific, printed with the quotation "Nothing is worth more than this day," attributed to Goethe. With an explanatory article in photocopy, "Goethe on a roll."
  - Plaques for portraits, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Brass plaques originally designed for the Oswald May portraits of Goethe and Wieland, now hanging in the north corridor, court level, of the Beinecke Library.
  - Paper ephemera related to Goethe/Schiller coins and medals, early twentieth century, undated (Box 1, Folder 12-13)
    Related Archival Materials note
    Also stored in: Oversize, Box 10
    Advertisements, rubbings, illustrations, photographs; some pieces relate to items in the Speck Collection.
  - Calling cards and coats of arms, undated; 5 items (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Includes calling cards of Walther von Goethe and Wolfgang Freiherr von Goethe
  - Textor, Johann Jost (1739-92). Printed ribbon celebrating his marriage to Maria Magdalena Möller on 17 February 1766, 1766, 1936; 1 letter (6 pages on 3 leaves), and 1 ribbon (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Provenance: old note says that this was placed on deposit by Kurt Textor.
    Pink ribbon, knotted in the middle, with four printed panels. Johann Jost Textor was Goethe's maternal uncle. With an ALS from Maria Textor to Carl Schreiber, 27 November 1936, describing a family ring and her current difficulties.
  - Tintner, Hans. Die Jugendgeliebte (Goethes Frühlungstraum), circa 1935; 15 photographs (23 x 29 cm.) (Box 1, Folder 16)
    15 photographs from the 1930s film, written and directed by Tintner (Atlantas-Film, Berlin)
  - Schiller, Friedrich. A swatch from his last waistcoat, undated; 4 x 8 cm. (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Lilac-colored silk cloth, with a signed authentication by Schiller's youngest daughter, Emilie von Gliechen Russwurm
  - Goethe, Johann Wolfgang von. Three pens used by him, 1818 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Three quills in a box with slipcase, with the inscription "Drey Federn, gebraucht bey Festgedichten Dec. 1818 Berga a.d. Ilm aufbewahrt durch Herren Schütz anerkannt Weimar Dec. 1827 von Goethe"
  - Faust and Mephistopheles. Metal cutout with etched lines, undated; Irregular shape, ca. 13 x 14 cm. (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Illustrations of miscellaneous Goethe-related items, including china, a ring, his coach, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Gretchen and Faust. Ornate metal wall hanging, 1898; Irregular shape, ca. 9 x 16 cm. (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Faust and Gretchen in the garden. Round plaque, non-metal, undated; 10 cm. (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Gretchen (?). Intaglio ceramic plaque, oblong, undated; 12 x 16 cm. (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Gretchen at the spinning wheel. Reproduction of a painting, mounted in glass, undated; 12 x 16 cm. (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Faust in his study. Oil painting on wood after the frontispiece to Goethe's Faust. Ein Fragment (1790), itself an adaptation of Rembrandt by Lips., undated; 21 x 16cm (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Dietrich, J. E. Gretchen im Kerker. Oil painting on wood, undated; 24 x 20 cm. (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Faust and Gretchen in the garden. Painting on glass, undated; 25 x 20 cm. (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Schweninger, Carl, the younger (1854-1903). Faust and Margarete, reproduction of an oil painting, on board, undated; 32 x 20 cm. (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Reinhart, Johann Christian, Schiller in Carlsbad, engraving after an original drawing, showing Schiller sitting on a mule, smoking a pipe, undated; 19 x 13 cm. (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Faust and Gretchen embracing. Two lithophanes, one alabaster (?) in a wood frame, the other dark blue plastic-like material, undated; 17 x 20 cm.
    Existence and Location of Originals
    Stored in: Oversize, Box 10
  - Faust and Gretchen in the garden, oil painting, undated; 15" x 10"
    Stored in: Oversize, Box 11
  - Faust and Gretchen in the street, colored print, undated; 16" x 12"
  - Four photographs of a staging of Christian Dietrich Grabbe's Don Juan und Faust, Meiningen, 1896 (Box 3, Folder 30-31)
  - Carving of Schiller's head, in profile, ivory, mounted in box, undated (Box 3, Folder 32)
    Custodial History
    Provenance: "Bequeathed by Mrs. Mary D. Turlay – received from Mrs. David T. Mackie (through Tiffany & Co) Nov. 26, 1921" Acquired in Heidelberg in the 1870s by Mrs. Mackie's mother.
    Accompanied by letter from Isabel Mackie to Mr. Dana, 1921 November 22
- Goethe in Advertising, 1897-1949; Series II; (2 boxes)
  A collection of labels, wrappers, clippings, advertising trade cards and other ephemera using Goethe quotations or motifs from his works (chiefly Faust) in advertising and the promotion of products. A few pieces depict Schiller or Schiller and Goethe. The material dates overwhelmingly from the late nineteenth and early twentieth centuries.
  - Drinks, mineral waters & healthy potions, undated (Box 3, Folder 33)
    Including Sanatogen tonic, Henkell Trocken, and various wines
  - Cigars and smoking
    - Cigar box labels, cigar bands, advertisements, matchbook, 1949, undated (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - Two wooden cigar boxes ("Goethe" brand and "Margarethe" brand), a cigarette box, and two wax match boxes from around 1900 featuring scenes from Faust, circa 1900, undated (Box 9)
  - Chocolate and other sweets, undated (Box 3, Folder 35)
    Including Chocolade Marke "Gretchen" (Moser-Roth, Stuttgart) and Mignon Speise-Schokolade (David Söhne A,-G., Halle)
  - Restaurants, hotels, and guesthouses, undated (Box 3, Folder 36)
    Including the Goethe-Stube at the Hotel "goldener Adler" (Innsbruck) and various uses of Auerbachs Keller as a motif
  - Books, bookstores, bookplates, undated (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Clothing, shoes, perfume, etc., undated (Box 3, Folder 38)
    Including packaging for Faust nail polish stones and advertisements for the "Dalli" self-heating flat iron, which feature a humorously updated Gretchen
  - Calendars, 1903-1918, undated (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Other products, 1900-1919, undated (Box 3, Folder 40)
    Including Gretchen Lockennadeln, Steiners Paradiesbett, fire extinguishers, drug stores, gas lighting ("Mehr Licht"), the Fränkische Butter-Centrale (Lotte cutting bread and butter), Schreibmachine "Ideal" ("Schreib deinen Pakt mit Seidel & Naumann's 'Ideal'"); Göthe-Feder, pen nibs made by Heintzel & Blanckertz (Berlin); and commemorative Meissen porcelain items.
  - Unidentified products, clippings, quotations, 1897-1911, undated (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Advertising trade cards with Goethe motifs
    - A. Zuntz sel. Wwe., gebrannte Caffees (Bonn, Berlin, and Hamburg), undated; 8 items (Box 4, Folder 42)
    - American Tobacco Co., undated; 1 card, 2 copies (Box 4, Folder 43)
      "These pictures are packed in the brands of cigarettes manufactured by the American Tobacco Co."
    - Apotheker W. Ullrich's Baldrianwein, undated; 6 items (Box 4, Folder 44)
    - Bouillon Cibils ( Hamburg), undated; 6 items (Box 4, Folder 45)
    - Leibig Company's Fleisch-Extract (Antwerp and London), representing several series, in German and French, undated; 25 items (including some duplicates) (Box 4, Folder 46)
    - Sächsische Cartonnagen-Maschinen (Dresden), undated; 6 items (Box 4, Folder 47)
    - Other firms, undated; 7 items (Box 4, Folder 48)
      Including Weber's Carlsbader Kaffeegewürz; Jordan & Timaeus Zuckerwaaren-Fabrik, Thee-Import (Dresden and Bodenbach); Stollwerck's Adler-Cacao; Hildebrands deutscher Kakao (Berlin); Moser-Roth Cacao (Stuttgart?); Kinder-Garderobe Heinrich Esders (Dresden); Petzold & Aulhorn, Edda-Chocolade (Dresden); C. Lück, Gesundheits-Kräuter-Honig (Colberg)
- Postcards and Commercial Photographs, 1897-1956; Series III; (2 boxes)
  Series III. consists of postcards and commercially distributed photographs. Images are chiefly of characters in Faust, but there are also images of Goethe, Schiller, and places in Germany. Image formats include lithographs, photographic postcards, and carte-de-visite and cabinet card photographs.
  - A collection of mostly early twentieth-century postcards relating to Goethe and Schiller, predominantly scenes from Goethe's Faust depicting Gretchen but also including places, portraits, and cards with purportedly humorous content, 1899-1956, undated; circa 185 items (Box 4, Folder 49-56)
  - A collection of mostly early twentieth-century postcards relating to Goethe and Schiller, predominantly scenes from Goethe's Faust depicting Gretchen but also including places, portraits, and cards with purportedly humorous content, 1899-1956, undated; circa 185 items (Box 5, Folder 57-59)
  - A small collection of commercial studio photographs, showing mostly various actresses portraying Gretchen, but including other subjects, 1897-1903, undated; circa 15 items (Box 5, Folder 60-61)
- Objects, 1897-1989; Series IV; (4 boxes)
  Objects consists of a wide range of three-dimensional items, including Goethe's grandfather's wax seal, images of Goethe reproduced in and on various media, figurines of characters from Faust, a fragment of Goethe's house, pressed flowers from Goethe's garden, a lock of Schiller's hair, a player piano roll, and fragments of the Berlin wall.
  - Brooch depicting Gretchen and Faust, oval, undated; 3.5 x 4x5 cm. (Box 6)
  - Fragment from Goethe's family house in Frankfurt. Irregular piece of red brick., undated; ca. 4 x 7 cm. (Box 6)
    Provenance: Gift of Dr. Arthur Burkhard
  - Textor, Johann Wolfgang (1693-1771). His seal for embossing wax, oval, undated; 2 cm. (Box 6)
    Provenance: old note in a card file says that this was deposited by Kurt Textor.
    J. W. Textor was Goethe's maternal grandfather.
  - Snuff box with image of Goethe, undated (Box 6)
  - Specimen of goethite (HFeO2), the mineral named for Goethe, undated (Box 6)
  - Three miniatures on porcelain, two of Schiller, one of Goethe. (Goethe is badly chipped), undated (Box 6)
  - Schiller-Haar. Lock of blond hair, purportedly Schiller's, in a souvenir-type glass box (box is in poor condition), undated (Box 6)
  - Model of Goethe's family house in Frankfurt, metal, souvenir quality, undated (Box 7)
  - "Schepp's Cake Box", 14 x 13 x 11 inches (Box 34 (Art))
    Metal box showing Goethe and Schiller, and scenes showing "Dorothea," "Lotte," and "Lili."
  - Goethe statuette, porcelain. After Rauch. (Box 35)
  - Plaster plaques and profiles
    - Two identical round plaques showing Goethe ("Wolfgang von Göthe"), one painted dark brown, both chipped, undated; 11 cm. (Box 7)
    - Round plaque showing Goethe ("Iohann Wolfgang die Goethe aetatis suae LXVI Anno), undated; 12 cm. (Box 7)
    - Round plaque showing Gellert, glazed, undated; 9 cm. (Box 7)
    - Two similar plaster silhouettes of Goethe's head in profile, undated; circa 7 and 9 cm. (Box 7)
  - Berlin wall. Small fragments, 1989 (Box 7)
    Provenance: Gift of Wolfgang & Inge Braecklein, 1989
  - Zwerger, A. Wood carving representing Mephistopheles., undated; 30 cm. (Box 8)
    Provenance: gift of Mrs. William A. Speck
    Inscribed "A Zwerger, Salzburg"
  - Mephistophles. Small wooden figurine, conical shape., undated; 12 cm. (Box 9)
  - Set of Faust figurines. Jointed wooden figures on bases, 12-14 cm. high. Two representing Mephistopheles, two representing Faust, one representing Gretchen, undated (Box 9)
  - Goethe demitasse cup and saucer (no mark), undated (Box 9)
  - Goethe bust. Small porcelain souvenir-type artifact, stamped "Germany" on the back., undated; 13 cm. (Box 9)
  - Pressed flowers and leaves from Goethe's garden in Weimar and from other sites associated with Goethe., 1897 (Box 9)
    Provenance: Almost certainly collected and preserved by William A. Speck on his second trip to Europe
    Loose between glass or sealed in glass mounts, most dated March or April 1897. The collection includes at least two examples of the "durch-gewachsene Rose," a rose in which stem and leaves grow out through the flower. Goethe used this phenomenon as evidence for his botanical theory that all parts of a flowering plant are morphological variations of the leaf.
  - Gounod, Charles François. Faust Valse. Piano roll for player piano., undated (Box 9)
    Paraphrase de Concert by Franz Liszt. New York: The Aeolian Company (Piano 9798).
  - Wooden plaque with incised quotation from Goethe's letter to Lavater, 20 September 1780 ("Diese Begierde, die Pyramide meines Daseyns.. ."), undated; 9" x 21"
    This plaque was almost surely part of a large sculpture acquired in the centenary year of Goethe's death and described by Carl Schreiber in the Report of the Librarian of Yale University, 1932-33, as an "Etruscan Goethe stele entitled Goethe Geist." The artist was the American sculptor Nat Smolin (1890-1950), then resident in Paris. This piece did not easily weather the vicissitudes of taste. The current curator has never seen it, its whereabouts being unknown to her. Her predecessor, Hedwig S. Dejon, used to say that the stele had been transferred to the Yale University Art Gallery for storage.
    Stored in: Oversize, Box 12
- Posters and Broadsheets, 1897-1932; Series V; 21
  Series V. consists of large-format posters advertising Goethe-related productions and events.
  - Adolph Friedländer, Hamburg, printer. 4 large colored posters, early 20th century?, undated; circa 22" x 26" (Box 13 Broadside)
    Including: Nous arrivons. Avec Chambly, le célèbre illustionist (Mephisto), 2 magic show posters (Mephisto), François Röthig (magic show)
  - Mignon, film adaptation. French, 1926 June 19; 31" x 45" (Box 14 Broadside)
  - Mignon. Adaptation cinégraphque en 6 parties de Ernest Servaes d'après le chef d'oeuvre de Goethe. Colored poster, Paris, L'Affiche d'Art, undated; 52" x 48" (Box 15 Broadside)
  - Sächsisch-Thüringische Industrie und Gewerbe Ausstellung, Leipzig, 1897; 23" x 30" (Box 16 Broadside)
    "Auerbachs Keller," colored illustration signed B. Wennerberg. Verlag von Meisenbach Riffarth & Co.
  - Stein der Weisen... Illustrirte Halbmonatsschrift. A. Hartleben's Verlag Colored poster, (Faust in study)., undated; 25" x 19" (Box 17 Broadside)
    Vienna: Ch Reisser & M. Werthner (late 19th century)
  - Der weltberühmte historische Auerbachs Keller und... Weinrestaurant. Colored poster (Faust and Mephisto)., circa 1913; 36" x 25" (Box 18 Broadside)
    Illustration signed Wil Howard. Leipzig: Günther, Kirstein & Wendler, [1913?]
  - Mephistopheles. Polka française. Ernst Rost. Poster advertisement, in red and black, in English, for printed music., undated; 27" x 23" (Box 19 Broadside)
    Illustration signed Hans Unger, printed in Dresden.
  - Seidel & Naumann's Schreibmachine "Ideal." 2 colored posters advertising typewriters (Faust and Mephisto/pact scene), undated; 46" x 35" and 26" x 14" (Box 20 Broadside)
    Hamburg: Gerhard F. Adler and unidentified printer.
  - Gebrueder Ramann Weingrosshandlung (Erfurt). Poster advertising wine wholesaler (Goethe/Schiller trademark), undated; 19" x 24" (Box 21 Broadside)
  - Vienna: Goethe-Akademie-Comité. Composite portrait of eight men, undated; 16" x 12" (Box 22 Broadside)
  - Emil Gutzkow Verlag (Stuttgart). Folded advertising broadsheet for Rudolf Presber's Das goldene Lachen, an anthology of humor published around 1915, circa 1915; 3 copies, 14" x 8" (Box 23 Broadside)